Shavua tov שבוע טוב Shavua tov everybody and chodesh tov חודש טוב
Chodesh tov today's daf דף daf is daf lamed-bet דף ל"ב daf
lamed-bet we pick up at the bottom of lamed-alef ל"א lamed-alef amud-bet
עמוד ב amud-bet
and the Gemara גמרא Gemara says like this
about five lines from the bottom. Amar lei Shmuel leChiya bar Rav
אמר ליה שמואל לחייא בר רב Amar lei Shmuel leChiya bar Rav
so in the middle of course what
about the old Armenians?
We did that. What?
About the old Armenians.
Yeah well yesterday of course right I mean anyway right so so
it was all about the issue about transporting the wine and who's
gonna you know concern about seals and who's gonna tamper with it
and so on okay and along the way yesterday we sort of
made it explicit which was sort of implicit that even a non-Jew
touching the wine makes it problematic. All right and we also dealt
with issues about whether something is assur behana אסור בהנאה assur behana
or not assur behana אסור בהנאה assur behana and pretty much you
know the basic story is that the wine is assur behana אסור
בהנאה assur behana except you know the Gemara גמרא Gemara dealt with
a scenario about
what do you call it about
as a concern that maybe he touched it you know and so
on that might allow for it to be in a middle state
that you can't drink it but you can get hana הנאה hana
although that was never fully explicated. So now we pick up five
lines from the bottom of lamed-alef ל"א lamed-alef amud-bet עמוד ב. amud-bet.
Amar lei Shmuel leChiya bar Rav אמר ליה שמואל לחייא בר רב
Amar lei Shmuel leChiya bar Rav so Shmuel שמואל Shmuel said to
Chiya bar Rav חייא בר רב Chiya bar Rav bar aryei בר
אריה bar aryei son of a lion tav ve'eima lach milta meialyata
de'avi amar rav avucha תא ואיימא לך מילתא מעלייתא דהוה אמר רב
אבוך. tav ve'eima lach milta meialyata de'avi amar rav avucha. Let me
tell you some a great thing that your Rav רב Rav your
father said because you're a son of a lion you're a son
of Rav רב Rav so I'm going to teach you a great
teaching that your father said. Hachi amar avucha הכי אמר אבוך hachi
amar avucha did I just do this? I did this yesterday. All
right fine we'll read it and finish the sentence whatever. Hachi amar
avucha hanei amaizee kun'ai dehavi shesu giluya velo meisi הכי אמר אבוך
הני אמגוזי כונאי דהוו שתו גילויא ולא מיתי hachi amar avucha hanei
amaizee kun'ai dehavi shesu giluya velo meisi because part of the whole
discussion yesterday was about giluy גילוי giluy those fat you know non-Jews
that drink exposed you know the exposed water and they don't die
so you'll say oh that proves there's not a problem with giluy
גילוי giluy no. It has to do with their non-Jewish constitution okay
adi de'achlei shekatzim uremasim chavilei gufaihei אדי דאכלי שקצים ורמשים חביל גופייהו
adi de'achlei shekatzim uremasim chavilei gufaihei since they eat all these disgusting
animals and maybe some of the animals are even poisonous or whatever
you know that destroys their body or somehow I don't know but
it builds up antibodies as well anyway. Okay amar Rav Yosef אמר
רב יוסף amar Rav Yosef last line of lamed-alef ל"א lamed-alef amud-bet
עמוד ב. amud-bet. Okay hai chala deshichra האי חלא
דשיכרא hai chala deshichra since we were talking about the whole issue
about sheichar שיכרא sheichar about beer and so on and a concern
about intermarriage but not a concern as we were talking about before
here that the beer per se is forbidden you know it's forbidden
in certain contexts to be drinking their beer you just step outside
of the store and it's okay still doesn't explain why Jews would
you know throughout you know centuries would drink beer in inns owned
by non-Jews and whatever but that's a separate conversation. Anyway hai chala
deshichra de'arma assur האי חלא דשיכרא דארמאי אסור hai chala deshichra de'arma
assur so vinegar of beer of non-Jews is forbidden why dema'arvi bei
durdaya de'yayin nesech דמערבי ביה דורדייא
דייין נסך dema'arvi bei durdaya de'yayin nesech because they mix with it
the lees the grape skins you know whatever of what they call
yayin nesech יין נסך yayin nesech it doesn't literally mean yayin nesech
יין נסך yayin nesech it really means stam yeinam סתם יינם stam
yeinam sometimes stam yeinam סתם יינם stam yeinam you know their plain
wine is referred to as yayin nesech יין נסך yayin nesech because
it's forbidden as an extension of wine that they directly poured. But
anyway because sometimes there's some grape additives to their beer to their
vinegar their beer vinegar not the beer itself that was just a
concern of intermarriage because there's some sometimes some grape additives you it's
forbidden. Amar Rav Ashi אמר רב אשי amar Rav Ashi said Rav
Ashi ume'otzar shari ומאוצר שרי ume'otzar shari but if they are getting
it from their like their warehouses they're getting their beer vinegar okay
it's permissible why keivan dema'arvi bei mistari כיון דמערבי ביה
מיסרייא keivan dema'arvi bei mistari because they don't add the grape the
grape additives those the lees or whatever it is they don't add
it for stuff they're putting into storage because then it'll just make
it spoil sooner somehow that additive will make it spoil sooner. So
if they're going to add it they would add it if and
they're taking it from storage they'll add it after they take it
after you know they you know they they take it from storage
and then they might add it afterwards but they don't add it
in storage okay and therefore you can be certain that this doesn't
have that grape additive. You know these are the types of discussions
that you have when you don't have hechsher הכשר hechsher industries and
this was the reality you know for centuries and centuries and even
until today to some degree the reality in Europe is that you
don't feel that you can figure out every single detail you don't
think you're in a position to know every single detail and you
make certain assumptions about how how things operate okay and since we
can assume that they don't add grape stuff you know you know
at this stage the stuff they keep in storage it doesn't have
grape stuff we go ahead and drink it yeah.
Who are the armee ארמאי? arma'a?
I
I've never figured out why arma'a ארמאי arma'a Armenian is sometimes used
to refer it doesn't mean Armenian it means a non-Jew generically but
I don't know why it uses that term sometimes sometimes it uses
goy גוי goy and sometimes it uses parsi'in פרסאי parsi'in when it's
being more specific but arma'a ארמאי arma'a is sort of like the
generic and I don't I haven't really figured out why that becomes
a generic.
No no no okay so anyway so let's take a look at
Tosafot תוספות Tosafot for some practical application okay Tosafot תוספות Tosafot says
hai chala deshichra de'arma assur האי חלא דשיכרא דארמאי אסור hai chala
deshichra de'arma assur so this Armean sheichar שיכרא sheichar by the way
the implication being that other sheichar שיכרא sheichar is permissible against the
previous Gemara גמרא Gemara again maybe it means after you've taken it
home you know that that tech that issue but you know it
is funny right away in the Gemara גמרא Gemara you know we're
discussing about how how people are always find you know have through
the centuries basically you know somehow bracketed this whole prohibition. In the
גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* you have like one who says that it's because
of בנות עכו"ם *benosei akum*, but you step outside of the door
it's okay. Then you had the position that it's because of גילוי
*giluy*, but it's really not a concern of גילוי *giluy* because the
hops neutralize it, you know? And here the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* basically
says, okay, it's a concern if you're afraid that there's some grape
additive, but sounds like in general it's not a concern.
I'm surprised it doesn't have a כשרות kashrus *kashrus* anything. He's the
hold.
I understand, I don't know what to tell you. Anyway, he says
היכא דשיכרא דמיא *haicha d'shichra d'maya*. So here תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says
צריך להזהר בשכר דבש *tzrich lehizaher beshichra devash* שקורין *shekorin* מיט *meet*,
which is mead, okay, לבדוק אם מטילים בו שמרי יין *livdok im
matilim bo shimrei yayin*. So therefore, since the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
that they would sometimes do this with beer vinegar, therefore תוספות Tosafot
*Tosafot* says in some way similar you have to do it, you
have to check out the mead that they use. Do they ever
add some types of grape leaves to it להעמיד מהר *le'hamid maher*
to cause it to make, I guess, ferment quicker? I guess that's
why maybe you'd add a little grape, you know, gets fermentation going
the same way that's how you make wine. כי יש מקומות שעושים
כן *ki yesh mekomos she'osim ken*, there are places that actually do
this. ואז ודאי הוא אסור assur *ve'az vadai hu assur*, then it's
forbidden. So
it's really not because of the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*. It's really because
תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says, hey, you know, there's a case, I actually
know that some places they do this with mead, so I want
to put everybody on an alert, כשרות kashrus, *kashrus* alert. Okay, the
כשרות *kashrus* alert is not that this product is bearing a U
but it's actually not okay. The כשרות *kashrus* alert is, here's places
where you might have a concern. Otherwise, you can buy their mead,
but here's places where you can't. The other תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* is
ומאוצר שרי דמיסתקרי *ume'otzar shari d'mistakari*, and but if they get it
from the warehouse it's okay because if it had the additive in
it it would spoil. So he says, הילכך נראה דמותר לקנות כל
מיני משקה *hilkach nira demutar liknos kol minei mashkeh* מן עובדי כוכבים
*min ovdei kochavim*. You can buy all the different types of of
of drinks from a non-Jew, you know, go go get a coffee,
get a tea, get some apple juice, some orange juice, some pineapple
juice. I'm not saying this for now, but that's what תוספות Tosafot
*Tosafot* was saying, okay. I mean, certainly coffee and tea we generally
feel you go into any store you buy coffee or tea, you
know, you don't start worrying if it's flavored. Anyway, כגון יין תפוחים
ומי
תותים *kegon yayin
tapuchim umei tutim*, for example, apple juice and strawberry juice. ובלבד *uvelvad*,
don't start worrying, oh my God, they might have added stuff. Why?
Because תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* is assuming, and I have no idea if
the reality is the same, but he's assuming since the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says the stuff here they keep in storage they don't add
wine to because it'll spoil, so that's true about other stuff as
too. Clearly wine additives or grape or grape, you know, what is
it called, skins or whatever, it'll cause spoilage sooner. So therefore when
you get liquids you don't have to concern yourself about possible wine
additives, okay, unless you know otherwise like the previous תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot*
said. ובלבד שיראה ישראל מושך מן החבית *uvelvad sheyireh Yisrael moshech min
hachavit*, as long as you see them, you the Jew see the
non-Jew taking it out of the barrel. Right, if they make it
in front of you? No, it is not making it in front
of you. It was stored in the barrel. He's assuming anything stored
does not have grape additives based on this גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. And
therefore if they're taking it out of something that's been stored. דוקא
*davka* if it's fresh it might be a problem. Okay. If not,
he's, no,
that's different. But if somehow it's fresh but hasn't been stored and
you know hasn't been stored, okay, then
then that might be an issue. But if it's stored, he says
you don't have to be concerned about grape additives as long as
you see them taking it out of the barrels directly. Okay, מן
החבית *min hachavit*. ואפילו דמיהם יקרים יותר מן היין *ve'afilu dmeihem yekarim
yoser min hayayin*, even if it's more expensive than wine. Why? What's
the point? Because if it's more expensive than wine, maybe you'll be
afraid that they basically took out some of the, you know, some
of the apple cider and mixed in some wine, because if wine
was cheaper?
No, because nevertheless דודאי לא עירבו יין בתוך החבית דמיסתקרי *devadai lo
irvu yayin betoch hachavit d'mistakari*. The stuff in storage definitely does not
have wine or grape additives because it would cause it to spoil.
He's asserting that based on what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says about
the beer, you know, or the vinegar. אבל אם לא ראהו מושך
מן החבית *aval im lo ra'ahu moshech min hachavit*, if you didn't
see him take, he'll say I'll go to the I'll go to
the back, you know, to the to the storage room and I'll
get you out and I'll bring you out some, then it's a
problem, then אז הדבר מתחלק *az hadavar mischalek*, then it depends. Okay.
במשקה היקר מן היין *bemashkeh hayakar min hayayin*, if he's going back
to the back room and getting you out some apple cider and
apple cider goes for more than wine, then even though he's getting
it out of a barrel, but if you don't see what he's
doing, יאסר שמא עירב בו יין *ye'aser shema eirev bo yayin*, you
have to be afraid that maybe he mixed in some wine. Watered,
like you ever hear of watering down the drinks? So that you'd
be afraid he watered it down with wine. להשתכר או להרויח *lehistaker
o leharviach* in order to make a greater profit. אבל אם היין
יקר *aval im hayayin yakar*, but if wine is more expensive, then
אין לחוש שמא עירב בו יין להכשילו *ein lachush shema eirev bo
yayin lehachshilo*, you don't have to be afraid that he mixed wine
just to cause you to sin. Okay, so here you go. Basically
תוספות Tosafot. *Tosafot* takes takes this גמרא Gemara *Gemara* and assumes based
on this we'll assume that any type of a drink that is
being stored that is being stored away, you know, and therefore and
therefore that has no wine additives because the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is
clear that wine or grape additives would cause it to spoil. He
just assumes across the board that's true about all drinks. And then
the only concern you have is if you don't see him taking
it out of the barrel, you know, maybe he added some wine
at that stage, and now he wouldn't do it just סתם *stam*
to make a sin, but he might do it in order to,
you know, in order to make a profit. You might that might
be a form of watering down. And if that's and if that's
a concern, no. And if that's a concern then you don't have
to, then you can't drink it. Beer is only a problem in
the בנותיהם context like we've been talking about. You know, that's, I
mean, it's clear from the גמרא. Gemara I mean, the גמרא didn't
discuss it, but like having the תערובת taroves of beer is not
an issue, that's my whole point. It's not אסור as the, as
a food. Okay. So now we go on to the next case
in the משנה. Mishna. וחרס הדרייני. V'cheres hadiyani.
And the other thing that is forbidden even in benefit is this
pottery of הדרייני. Hadiyani.
So מאי הדרייני? mai hadiyani? What is הדרייני? hadiyani? אמר רב יהודה
אמר שמואל חרס של אדריינוס
קיסר, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel cheres shel Hadrianos keisar, pottery of
Hadrian, the Caesar Hadrian. Okay, now what does that mean? So now
we're going to explain it. כי אתא רב דימי אמר, Ki ata
Rav Dimi amar, when Rav Dimi came from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
he explained it the following way:
קרקע בתולה הייתה שלא עבד אדם מעולם. Karka besula hayta shelo avda
adam me'olam. This is what happened, this is how this Hadrianic pottery
was made. You started with some land that had never been, you
know, virgin soil. Right. So therefore it had its full powers, all
of its nutrients.
עבדה, Avda, so they plowed it or whatever, you know, they cultivated
it. ונטעה, V'nat'a, they planted it with, you know, grapevines. ורמי
ליה לחמרא, V'rami lei lechamra, and then they got wine out of
it. So the wine that they're going to get out of this
is going to be super, super strong wine because it's from a
land that has all of its nutrients. Okay, and then they took
the wine that they got out of the grapes that came from
this land, בגופי חיוורי b'gufi chivri in white types of pottery
vessels, ומצלי להו לחמריהו. umatzlei lehu lechamraihu. And this white pottery was
somehow very absorbent and it sucked up all the wine into it.
ומתברי להו בחספי, Umitru lehu b'chafsabi, and then what they did is
they took the pottery and they broke the pottery into little pieces
of pottery because now the pottery is totally absorbed in wine. This
is basically how, you know, you would make like dehydrated milk or
something, you're traveling, so you dehydrate it and just add water. Okay,
so here they had dehydrated wine or whatever, just add water. They
had it in little pieces of pottery, okay. ודרו בהדייהו, V'daru b'hadaihu,
and they carried it with them, these pieces of pottery. וכל היכא
דמטו, V'chol heicha d'mato, wherever they would go, the army on their,
you know, in their travels, טרו להו ושתו, Taru lehu v'shatu, they
would drop the piece of pottery into water, they'd absorb, you know,
they'd immerse it in water and then it'd turn into wine. And
then they would have wine wherever they would have to go. Okay,
the Roman army travels on its belly, okay, on its palate, I
guess. All right,
anyway. So, so, I have, I saw somebody once had a t-shirt
that said, instant human, just add coffee. All right, anyway. So אמר
רבי יהושע בן לוי, amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, וראשון
שבהן, v'rishon she'bahen, our first quality wine, our top wine is כשלישי
שלהן, kishlishi she'lahen, is only equivalent to their like third quality wine
or the third degree derived maybe from these pottery shards, these pottery
shards of such, it's like so strong, so intense. Okay, anyway. איבעיא
להו, Iba'ye lehu, they asked, מהו לסמוך בהן כרעי המיטה? mahu lismoch
bahen karia d'mita? When we say these pottery shards are forbidden, how
much do we literally mean that they're forbidden? Do we mean that
we're like treating it as wine itself and therefore you can't even
use these pottery shards, I don't know, to like scratch an itch
or to support, you know, if you have a bed that's a
little wobbly and you put it under one leg of the bed?
You're using it then as pottery, you're not using it as wine.
So in a way what it's asking is, is like if you
sort of, you know, can, is it just that it's forbidden in
a way that I would somehow get benefit from the wine in
it? You know, like if I put it in water or something
like that, I can't drink the wine. Or are you saying even
as pottery it's forbidden because we're treating it as if it's the
wine itself? Okay.
We see the same thing about anything else besides that?
תוספות Tosafot has a whole discussion about whether you apply that to
other types of things. Okay, I mean not other types of things
in general but other things within this wine discussion. But the point
here is, you're right, it might be a particular, very few things
are אסור מהנאה assur m'hana'ah anyway, but you know, if you're right,
like if you had something like a piece of pottery that had
absorbed בשר בחלב basar b'chalav taste or whatever, we presumably would not
be a problem. It's presumably a special stringency related to עבודה זרה.
avoda zara. But the reason the גמרא is asking it is because,
well first of all, we say that this has absorbed it so
much. So if it's absorbed it so much, it's not just like
a pot that you cooked בשר בחלב basar b'chalav and a little
taste could come out. This is like, you know, this from this
they would actually turn, make, you know, make wine out of it.
So maybe we consider it like, so one thing has to do
with the מציאות, metzius, that the, you know, the actual case that
they describe, they see the thing as wine itself. And the other
might have to do with the stringency of the category. Since it's
related to סתם יינם stam yeinam and יין נסך yayin nesech and
whatever, they might be treating it in a more weighty way. And
they're also responding to the language of the משנה. Mishna. The משנה
Mishna says that this pottery is forbidden, right? It doesn't say if
you get any, if you get any wine extract from the pottery.
So that's why they're asking the question. רוצה בקיומו ידי דבר אחר
שריא או אסור. Rotzeh b'kiyumo yedei d'var acher sharya o assur. If
you want the pottery there, you're getting benefit from it, but it's
for the other thing, meaning it's for the pottery of it, it's
not for the wine of it, is that permissible or forbidden? תא
שמע Ta shma come in here, דרבי אליעזר ורבי יוחנן חד אסר
וחד שרי, D'Rabbi Eliezer v'Rabbi Yochanan chad assur v'chad sharya, it's a
bit of Rabbi Eliezer and Rabbi Yochanan. And now of course these
three words is a whole debate about whether these words were
in the גמרא. A lot of the הלכתאs Hilchasa in the בבלי
Bavli were גאוני Geonic glosses, were not in the original text. Okay,
so anyway, so that presumably is what this is, and that's why
there's a debate why they've
been very מחמיר machmir on this so far. I understand.
מיתיבי. Meisvei. Okay, now the גמרא's going to say I'll ask you,
you know, to the position that says that it's forbidden.
הדרדורין, Hardardurin, which is like some types of basically like barrels,
והרקבאות, v'ha-rokva'os, which is some types of a, also like a, a
wine skin, you know, a leather flask, okay, של עובדי כוכבים, shel
ovdei kochavim, of the non-Jews, יין שישראל כנוס בהן, yayin she'yisrael kanus
ben, if you put your wine in it, now if you put
your wine in it, there's a concern that some of the absorbed
wine that was from those flasks or those barrels will now go
back into your wine. Now, if you think about normal כשרות issues,
you know, we would say, oh, fine, whatever, it's all cold, don't
worry about it, right? But by wine, again, it's possibly for this
stringency of wine, possibly because we are dealing, the reality of when
we're dealing with particularly pottery things, although here we're also dealing with
a leather flask, you know, there's like a lot of absorption and,
you know, and maybe therefore there's more of a concern that that
stuff that absorbed actually comes out even though everything is cold. So
here's the first example where we're seeing what does not follow normal
rules of כשרות, that even though everything is cold, there's a concern
that some of the absorbed wine will come out.
He used the Sherry cask question?
Sort of, yeah, yes. To some degree, yeah, basically. Okay, של עובדי
כוכבים, shel ovdei kochavim, good point, it's like, it is exactly like
the Sherry cask. Okay,
יין שישראל כנוס בהן, yayin she'yisrael kanus ben, if you are keeping
your wine in it, אסור בשתייה ומותר בהנאה, asur b'shtiya u'mutar b'hana'ah,
then you have to be afraid that some of the wine, the
non-Jewish wine absorbed in the walls will come into your wine, and
therefore you can't drink it but you can get benefit. Now once
again we are seeing this middle level, like, you know, it's not
the wine itself, it's some concern that some wine came out, so
why not just say אסור בהנאה? asur b'hana'ah? If you're afraid the
non-Jew touched it, say אסור בהנאה. asur b'hana'ah. So we're seeing sometimes
when there's either a middle level, either you don't know it was
touched by a non-Jew, some wine came out but it's maybe it's
a trace amount, maybe you don't know if the wine came out,
so there's this middle level of don't drink it but you can
derive benefit. Okay, but anyway, but that's point number one. העיד רבי
שמעון בן גודא לפני בנו של רבן גמליאל על רבן גמליאל, Heid
Rebbi Shimon ben Guda lifnei b'no shel Rabban Gamliel al Rabban Gamliel,
Rebbi Shimon Guda testified in front of Rabban Gamliel's son, he said,
let me tell you something about your father, ששתה ממנו בעכו, sheshasa
mimenu b'Akko, I saw him, you know, some non-Jew, he used these
flasks and he put his wine in it and he drank from
it in Akko, so I'm telling you it's totally permissible. ולא הודו
לו. V'lo hodu lo. And they didn't agree to him. You know,
now who is the they? It's not, it doesn't, it sounds like
the rabbis around, it's not clear what his son thought, or Rabban
Gamliel's son thought, but they said no, of course not, he never,
חס ושלום, chas v'shalom, Rabban Gamliel, he would have never done such
a thing. Okay, anyway. Okay, or it meant he did it but
we don't agree that that's the right thing to do. Okay, but
anyway, clearly there's a possibility out there that it's totally permissible. Is
there a way to kosher this? Yes, we're going to get to
that. Okay, anyway, נודות. nodos. By the way, but the point being
all of all of this is only a problem because maybe the
wine absorbed in it came out. It's not yet a problem that
the actual like leather or pottery itself was a problem.
נותן טעם? noten ta'am?
Well, that's the question. So it's all cold, remember. So part of
this question is if it's all cold, is it enough to come
out to create a problem? By normal types of things, if this
had been used to store בשר בחלב basar b'chalav soup and then
you kept your chicken soup in it and everything was cold, it
would not be a problem.
Can I ask this question? I'm trying to understand is like why
aren't we worried that they, you know, were מנסך menasech it in
front of another idol? This is not תשמישי עבודה זרה tashmishei avoda
zara like casks. No, no, no, no, no, it's the,
if it's like a pouch, right?
No, it's not תשמישי עבודה זרה. tashmishei avoda zara. Anyway, but that's
not the issue. There's not a real concern, if there's nothing concrete.
No, the נוד nod would itself be forbidden.
But there's not, we don't all of a sudden concern that they
do everything for עבודה זרה. avoda zara. The nature of the concern
expresses itself in the attitude towards סתם יינם stam yeinam and treating
it as a non-kosher food. It doesn't mean that we always say,
oh maybe he was מנסך menasech this and therefore this. Anyway it
wouldn't be תשמישי tashmishei because you're whatever it's like תשמיש דתשמיש tashmish
d'tashmish but anyway. Okay, so now the גמרא says like this.
Okay, now where were we? ולא הודו לו. v'lo hodu lo. נודות
של עובדי כוכבים. nodos shel ovdei kochavim. Now
if you have a flask of these non-Jews, I don't know exactly
how a flask is different than a רקבאת? rokva'os? No, הרקבאות, v'ha-rokva'os,
but whatever, some type of a leather flask. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
אומר משם רבי יהושע בן קפוסאי, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer mishum
Rebbi Yehoshua ben Kphusai, אסור לעשות מהם דבר אחר, asur la'asos mehem
davar acher, you can't use them, I'm sorry did I skip a
line? שקיחין לחמור, shachichim l'chamor, you can't use it as a type
of a saddle, you know, what do you call like a saddle
cushion, you know, not a cushion, whatever it would be. Anyway, a
saddle piece of leather, saddle cloth for your donkey. Okay, so there
look, it's a perfect example that it is, that you're not getting
benefit from the wine itself, just from the leather, and it's forbidden.
And by the way, this even sounds like what we were until
now, we were just talking about this very special case of the
Hadrianic wine, which is super absorbed and you know super high concentrated.
Here it sounds like anything that absorbed wine, even normal cases, normal.
So alright let's see where the גמרא *Gemara* goes with it. So
מותיב הכא דרוצה בקיומיה דדבר אחר ותניא דאסור *moseiv hacha de-rotze bikiyumei
dedavar acher vetanya de-assur*, so you see here that it's forbidden, so
doesn't this prove the side that says it's forbidden? The גמרא *Gemara*
says ולטעמיך *ve-lita'ameich* according to your reasoning קנקנים של עובדי כוכבים לצרור
למזבין *kankanim shel ovdei kochavim litzror limzbin*,
why we should be forbidden to buy you know to buy barrels
or whatever you know jugs from the non-Jews for and we know
that they used once to store their wine. And so מאי שנא
נוד ומאי שנא קנקנים *mai shna nod u-mai shna kankanim*, what's the
difference one or the other? So אמר רבא *amar Rava* here's the
difference and presumably taking for granted that they would buy the jugs
of the non-Jews, גזרה שמא יבקע נודו *gezeirah shema yibaka nodo* we're
afraid now
the reason for not using the leather flask as a type of
a saddle cloth is because we're afraid you'll be traveling with your
donkey, your wine flask will break ויטילנו ויתפרנו על גבי נודו *veyatilnu
veyitferenu al gabei nodo* and therefore you'll come and you'll take this
you the Jew will take this thing that had been used as
a saddle cloth and you'll you know you'll wrap it around your
flask because your flask has a leak in it, okay, and then
the wine in your flask then will absorb the taste that's in
this. So the basic point is that this really is not a
problem. We're not really saying you can't use the pottery itself, you
can't use the leather itself. What we're saying is in this one
case they didn't allow it because you know you don't go ahead
and if your pottery jug springs a leak you don't patch it
up with a piece of pottery, okay. So there they weren't concerned
but like a leather thing you might use it as a patch.
So that was a special גזרה *gezeirah*. But the basic rule is
that it's not a problem the thing itself, it's only a problem
the wine that comes from it. All right so that's how the
גמרא *Gemara* is defending the position that says that it's allowed to
use the thing itself and this forbidden to use it for a
donkey saddle was a special case. So the גמרא *Gemara* says למאן
דאמר רוצה בקיומיה דדבר אחר אסור *le-man de-amar rotze bikiyumei dedavar acher
assur*, now one minute, let's go back to the position that says
it is a problem to use the thing itself. מאי שנא קנקנים
דשרו *mai shna kankanim deshru*, so why do we so then how
do you explain why we can use normal types of
jugs, you know pottery jugs that we buy from the non-Jews? So
the גמרא *Gemara* says אמר לך *amar lach* he'll tell you התם
ליתיה לאיסורא בעיניה הכא איתיה לאיסורא בעיניה *hasam leseih le-issura be'einei hacha
iseih le-issura be'einei*, so finally it gets to a difference between the
מציאות metziut. *metzius*. It says a normal type of a jug that's
just normal low-level absorption. So if you know if you don't use
it in a way that the wine will come back out you
know it's fine. But in this case of the Hadrianic you know
types of pottery it is so strong, so intense, so concentrated that
it's like the actual wine itself, okay. So let me sort of
step back. So what you've got is within the Hadrianic pottery that
is highly concentrated we might look at it as wine itself and
therefore say don't even use the pottery you know to scratch an
itch or for your bed. We're treating it as if it's סתם
יינם *stam yeinam* itself. That's the debate
by the way. But by other types of stuff, normal cases of
absorption, okay, we would say you know don't use it for wine
and the taste will come back out you know and the חידוש
chiddush. *chiddush* there by the way is that taste is coming out
even in just cold transfer but to use it for other things
is okay. And the case about the donkey saddle that's some different
case. But what the גמרא *Gemara* is not clear about is on
the one hand it says we buy their קנקנים *kankanim*, we buy
their jugs, right. What do you think you do with a jug
that you buy from them?
You use it.
Thank you. So what's going on? You know a minute ago we
say don't use it to keep wine in because the wine taste
will come back out and now we're saying and then we just
said but why are we buying their jugs which presumably means you're
using their jugs? So put aside the issue of the Hadrianic stuff
and is it אסור בהנאה *assur behana'ah*. Let's just ask the question
of using their jugs that they used for their wine, do we
have to be concerned that when we use it with cold the
wine will come back out? So the גמרא *Gemara* is very there's
a huge תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* here of course, you know the גמרא
*Gemara* is very unclear you know you know ambiguous about that issue
about why is it you know why is it okay to use
their jugs to store our wine or not okay to use their
jugs to store our wine. Okay, so it does not really come
to a clear conclusion about that. Obviously whatever,
it's complicated, okay. It might have to do with how long of
storage you keep the wine in. You keep it in briefly, do
you keep it in for a long period of time and then
it takes it out, you know how might the particular materials whatever,
but it obviously it seems
inconsistent here.
Juices might draw it out,
right exactly, you know a lot of the circumstances might make a
difference. Was it cleaned beforehand? Well that wasn't exactly the concern, but
yes. Okay, so now the גמרא *Gemara* says like this, ולא הודו
לו *velo hodu lo*. Now back to this idea that they said
this גודא *Guda* said to Rabban Gamliel's son, oh your father used
to do it, no problem. And by the way, that could be
another answer. It could be that the position that says you can
use them is following the position of what was testified in the
name of רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel *Rabban Gamliel*, okay, there was actually
a debate about that maybe. Maybe this issue of buying the jugs
reflects a פסק *psak* like the story of רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel?
*Rabban Gamliel* in עכו *Akko*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says like this.
So that's, so they ורמינהי *v'ramini* now I'm going to challenge this
story that the sages did not concede to the position of you
know the testimony about רבן גמליאל's *Rabban Gamliel's* activity. Here we have
a different ברייתא *braita*. יין הבא ברוקבאות *Yayin ha-ba b'rukvot* wine that
is coming in these types of flasks, של עובדי כוכבים *shel ovdei
kochavim*, אסור בשתייה ומותר בהנאה *assur b'shtiya u'mutar b'hana'ah*. So it's your
wine stored in their flasks, you can't drink it but you can
derive benefit. העיד שמעון בן גודא *He'id Shimon ben Guda* לפני בנו
של רבן גמליאל *lifnei bno shel Rabban Gamliel* על רבן גמליאל *al
Rabban Gamliel* ששתה ממנו בעכו *she-shata mimeno b'Akko*. That he hey, your
father drank from this in עכו *Akko*. It's actually permissible to drink.
והודו לו *V'hodu lo*. And now we have a different end to
the story, that the sages actually admitted to him. So that yeah,
you're right, טאקע *takeh*, we take it back. So that could be
an explanation why we use the flasks because maybe in the end
they did agree to this testimony.
So מאי לא הודו לו דקאמר *mai lo hodu lo d'ka'amar*? So
now how do you reconcile these two stories? So the גמרא *Gemara*
has two answers. Answer number one: מאי לא הודו לו דקאמר *mai
lo hodu lo d'ka'amar*, when it says they didn't agree to him,
התם חבריא לא הודו לו אבל בנו מודה לו *hatam chavraya lo
hodu lo aval bno modeh lo*. So it means that the other
colleagues, the other rabbis didn't agree, but the son, he accepted the
testimony of his father. He says, you know what, that explains a
lot of things. Yeah, I accept that, I remember my dad doing
stuff like that. Okay, if you end the story that way, so
the other rabbis didn't agree but the son did agree, you would
be you're going to go to the position that it's going to
be forbidden, presumably. Okay, but here's version number two: איבעית אימא *Iba'it
eima*, if you want I can tell you, גודא לחוד וגודא לחוד
*Guda l'chud u'Guda l'chud*. One is spelled with an aleph, one is
spelled with an ayin, which is pretty funny. But anyway, and the
way רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says what it means, if you look at
רש"י Rashi *Rashi*, okay if you look at רש"י *Rashi*, גודא לחוד
וגודא לחוד, לזה לא הודו ולזה הודו אחרי כן *Guda l'chud u'Guda
l'chud, l'zeh lo hodu u'l'zeh hodu acharei khen*. First, the first testimony
came and the other rabbis didn't buy it. Then somebody else testified
the same thing. They said, you know what, טאקע *takeh*, maybe it
is true, and they accepted it. So according to that version, in
the end the conclusion might be that it's מותר בשתייה *mutar b'shtiya*,
which explains why we buy the barrels from them. So with the
exception of the Hadrianic and the very, very special case that we
might treat it like the wine itself, we might actually be saying
that you can store your wine in their barrels and in their
pottery, you know, flasks or whatever it is, and we're not afraid
that the taste will come back out. It's all cool. Okay, so
it's a really this big huge question, the conclusion remains a little
unclear. Now there's plenty of the גמרא *Gemara* at the end of
this מסכת *masechet* deals with these cases, but here's our first introduction
to it.
Wouldn't the fermentation process cause a chemical reaction that eats up in
some ways? It's not just...
No, but these are barrels that was used for being stored in.
This was not barrels, this was
not after it yeah, after it was made, right. It was not
in the process of making it. Okay, ועורות לבובין *V'orot levuvin*. Now
we get to take a break from סתם יינם *stam yeinam*, which
I'm like saying phew because anyway סתם יינם *stam yeinam* is the
hardest part of this מסכת *masechet*, and we got a little taste
of it, ha ha ha. Okay, a little Hadrianic pottery taste of
it because it's in the long list of things that we can't
get benefit from. But now we go back to things that are
not about סתם יינם *stam yeinam*, other types of food that either
you can't eat or can't get benefit from, and we're going to
revisit סתם יינם *stam yeinam* at the end of the מסכת *masechet*.
Okay, ועורות לבובין *V'orot levuvin*. Yeah, now we get into like classic
כשרות *kashrut* stuff. Okay, so now the other thing you can't get
benefit from is if you see a piece of leather that's got
a hole cut out and clearly was like opposite the heart of
the animal, then you can't get benefit because then you assume that
that was used in some idolatrous purpose, like you know, Indiana Jones
and the Temple of Doom. So I was just thinking so anyway,
apparently they would do something. They would cut it open, you know,
maybe while it was alive opposite the heart. So that was some
type of, you know, idolatrous practice. I mean, it was done it
was used in some idolatrous practice. תנו רבנן *Tanu rabanan*, the rabbis
taught: איזהו עור לבוב *Eizehu or lavuv*? What is a leather that
the heart space is cut out from
it? כל שקרוע כנגד הלב *Kol she'karua k'neged halev*.
He use the word לבובי *levuvi*, I guess.
That is exactly the word לבובי *levuvi*, yeah. וכדור כמין ארובה *V'kadur
k'min arubah*, and it's cut open like a type of a skylight
in a particular fashion. יש עליו קורט דם אסור *Yesh alav koret
dam assur*.
If there is this is sort of like
doing an autopsy if there's a drop of blood absorbed into the
leather, then it's forbidden, then you know it was cut when the
animal was alive. אין עליו קורט דם מותר *Ein alav koret dam
mutar*. If the leather is clean and there's no blood absorbed in
it, then מותר *mutar*, permissible. You know it was cut only after
the animal was flayed or else there would have been blood in
it. אמר רב הונא *Amar Rav Huna*: לא שנו אלא שאינו מלוח
*Lo shanu ela she'eino maluach*. It's only if you did they did
not treat the leather and salt it. Okay, אבל מלוח אסור *Aval
maluach assur*. If it's been treated with salting and so on, then
even if you don't see blood on it, it's forbidden. Why? אימר
מלחא אברתיה *Eimar milcha avrateih*. You can say that the salt caused
the blood to be, you know, to come away, to get drawn
out. So maybe it had the blood on it and it was
done when it was alive and you can't see it now. רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל *Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel*... רבן גמליאל אומר בזמן שהחתך
שלו עגול אסור משוך מותר. If it depends what the tear looks
like. If the tear is circular, it's forbidden, which did not sound
like it said before when it said like a skylight. Skylight makes
you think about square, whatever, and with flaps anyway, but he says
if it's a circular cut, that shows it was used in this
idolatrous purpose, if it's sort of like rectangular or something or you
know it's elongated, it's clearly not used for that way. אמר רב
יוסף אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל הלכה כרבן גמליאל. Amar Rav Yosef
amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel halacha k'Rabban Gamliel. We rule like this,
it's only when it's cut in a circular way it's a problem.
אמר ליה אביי. Amar lei Abaye. Abaye said to Rav Yosef, הלכה
מכלל דפליגי. halacha michlal d'pligi. So when you're saying we rule like
Rabban Gamliel, you're suggesting that he's disagreeing with the תנא קמא. Tanna
Kamma. Is that really true? Like I could easily have read Rabban
Gamliel just to be clarifying the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, not disagreeing
with him. אמר ליה. Amar lei. So Rav Yosef said back to
Abaye, מאי נפקא לך מינה? mai nafka lach mina? What difference does
it make if he's agreeing or disagreeing? If in the end we
rule like Rabban Gamliel, who cares whether he's clarifying or whether he's
disagreeing? אמר ליה. Amar lei. So Abaye said back, גמרא גמורי זמורתא
תהא? gemara gemorei zimurta tehei? You know, we know our teaching should
be like a little ditty, like a song? Meaning what, I'm supposed
to go around and say like oh we rule like
Rabban Gamliel like it's a little ditty even if it doesn't mean
anything? Like I'm not going to say that if it doesn't mean
anything. If Rabban Gamliel is just clarifying the position of תנא קמא,
Tanna Kamma, then I'm not going to say we rule like him.
You know, we need to be very precise about what it is
that we're saying even if there's no practical נפקא מינה. nafka mina.
Okay,
so now the הגמרא Gemara says like this: בשר הנכנס לעבודת כוכבים
מותר. basar hanichnas l'avodat kochavim mutar. Now trying to get a little
more direct about the acts. If the person is you see a
non-Jew and here is his temple of Zeus and he's saying and
I'm bringing this meat, where are you going? I'm going for my
worship today at the temple of Zeus and I've got this two
pounds of meat and somehow then if you buy that a steak
off of him before he brings it into the temple, I mean
you can't eat it because he shechted it it's whatever, but you
can go ahead and like buy it from him and like I
don't know you're in the wholesale business and you sell it to
somebody else you can get הנאה hana'ah from it, okay? Even though
he's on his way to bringing it to the temple of Zeus.
But then an hour later he comes out and he's bringing his
meat, then you assume it was put as an offering, presumably even
after they offered it up they would then take it back, I
don't know what that would be, okay? And then you have to
assume it was given as an offering and then it's forbidden in
הנאה. hana'ah. Okay,
so the Gemara says בשר הנכנס לעבודת כוכבים מותר. basar hanichnas l'avodat
kochavim mutar. מאן תנא? man tanna? Who's the
Tanna? אמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן דלא כרבי אלעזר.
Amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan d'lo k'Rabbi Elazar. Not
like Rabbi Elazar. דאי כרבי אלעזר, d'ei k'Rabbi Elazar, הא אמר סתם
מחשבת עבודת כוכבים לעבודת כוכבים. ha amar stam machshevet avodat kochavim l'avodat
kochavim. We have to assume when a non-Jew slaughters an animal he
is doing it thinking like even if he's going ahead and he's
got a butcher shop, we have to be afraid that when he's
slaughtering his meat he's thinking this should be as an offering to
Zeus. Okay, and therefore according to that position, any meat that was
ever slaughtered by a non-Jew is treated like meat offered to עבודה
זרה avoda zara because the act of slaughtering, that's a classic act
of worship, slaughtering an animal to your god and therefore that meat
is a type of an offering to a god and therefore the
meat is forbidden in benefit. So according to him it's always forbidden
in benefit. That's clearly not the assumption of our משנה. Mishnah. Actually
our משנה Mishnah goes even further. Even meat that is now being
brought into the temple we don't have to be concerned that when
it was slaughtered this morning it was done as an offering to
the god. As meat it's being brought to the god, but the
act of slaughtering was not that even if the guy was intending
to use this meat this way, that's a pretty big חידוש. Okay,
so we're not concerned that it was brought that the slaughtering was
done as that act and therefore the meat is permissible in benefit.
Yes, you say the same thing as like let's say he's coming
in, you know, he went to the kosher butcher store, he's coming
out with a package all wrapped and you know now he's going
with this meat would you be able to buy, you know
would you say the same thing? Maybe, it all depends on the
מציאות. metzius, Okay, והיוצא אסור מפני שהוא כזבחי מתים. v'hayotzei asur mipnei
shehu k'zivchei meitim. Once he takes it out though it's forbidden, that's
like something that is זבחי מתים. zivchei meitim. Again that phrase is
used of something offered, you know, to the dead. It's probably keeping
in line that's a phrase in the תורה, Torah, but you know
probably a way of signifying like these gods are meaningless and so
on.
Anyway it's an offering to the gods and therefore you can't get
benefit from it. מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? What's the reason? אי אפשר
לליקוט של עבודת כוכבים. ei efshar l'likut shel avodat kochavim. It's impossible
that while he went into that temple
he didn't use it in some way as an offering to the
god. Again why he's now taking it back out, I don't know.
Okay, מני? mani? Now who's this going like? רבי יהודה בן בתירה
היא. Rabbi Yehuda ben Beteira hi. It's Rabbi Yehuda ben Beteira. דתניא
רבי יהודה בן בתירה אומר, d'tanya Rabbi Yehuda ben Beteira omer, מנין
לתקרובת עבודת כוכבים שמטמא באהל? minayin l'tikrovet avodat kochavim she'metamei b'ohel? How
do you know that a something that is an offering, you know,
to the gods is forbidden is treated as טמא? tamei? We discussed
this when we did the משנה, Mishnah, right? It's not just that
it's and the Gemara when the Gemara discuss יין נסך yayin nesech
it discussed that it was טמא. tamei. The association with עבודה זרה
avoda zara and טומאה, tumah, right, it's completely as off limits, completely
like taboo. It creates even, you know, even real טומאה. tumah. שנאמר.
she'ne'emar. Anyway, how do you know that it causes it's like a
dead body? It causes טומאה tumah even if you're under Under the
same roof as it. שנאמר: shene'emar: ויצמדו לבעל פעור ויאכלו זבחי מתים.
Vayitzmadu le'Ba'al Pe'or vayochlu zivchei meitim. They cleaved unto בעל פעור Ba'al
Pe'or and they ate the sacrifice to the dead. So there, the
sacrifice to the god is like a dead body. מה מת מטמא
באהל אף תקרובת עבודה זרה מטמא באהל. mah meit metamei be'ohel af
tikroves avodah zarah metamei be'ohel. Here too, it causes טומאה tumah under
a roof. Now the question is, what does this have to do
with anything? You know, we're not talking about טומאה. tumah. We're talking
about that you can't get benefit from it. Okay, and our משנה
mishnah and what? Does anybody disagree that you can't get benefit with
תקרובת עבודה זרה? tikroves avodah zarah? So that's what תוספות Tosafot has
a whole discussion of, meaning what it sounds like the גמרא is
saying is, okay, and this is the way רש"י explains it,
since we're comparing it to a dead body to say that it
causes טומאה, tumah, also causing it to a dead body to say
it's not permissible to derive benefit from it. But the fact that
we have to ascribe this to who are we ascribing it to?
רבי יהודה בן בתירה Rabbi Yehuda ben Beseira makes it sound like
there's some opinion out there that you can derive benefit from things
that are offered as an offering to the gods. Who the heck
says that? Nobody says that. Anything offered as תקרובת, tikroves, everybody agrees
it's forbidden in benefit. Okay, big question. So that's תוספות's Tosafot question.
So תוספות has two answers, and I'm remembering one and I'll check
the other. One answer תוספות says
is that here's the difference: a classic תקרובת tikroves offering is something
that is done as something we recognize as a classic form of
worship, slaughtered, an animal slaughtered to the gods like bringing a sacrifice,
throwing the blood, pouring יין נסך, yain nesech, putting it up on
an altar, burning it on an altar. This was none of that.
This guy takes some meat that he got in the butcher store,
he walks in, he puts it down, who knows what he does,
and then he picks it up and he leaves out. Is that
a real offering to the gods? Right? It's not a classic act
of worship that we would recognize. Now, when we learn סנהדרין, Sanhedrin,
we learn who cares whether we think it's classic or not, maybe
that's what they do. But anyway, תוספות is saying that's why you
had to quote this idea of treating it like a dead body.
Now I don't know how treating it like a dead body gives
an answer to that, but anyway, it sort of underscores that if
you're going to say this thing causes טומאה tumah under a tent,
it means you're taking a very strict approach to this whole category
and therefore you'll extend it even to things that you did something
like this with it and even that you didn't do an actual
act of like real worship. I do have to tell you, by
the way, this reminds me of years ago, decades ago maybe now
even, I don't know if people remember when this whole thing about
not buying hair wigs that came from India because there was a
sense that they've shaved it in some type of a practice, etc.
So that would be an interesting example, right? Does that make it
forbidden in benefit if they go into the temple and shave it?
Is that an act of תקרובת, tikroves, of offering it up? So
תוספות says that's a little bit of what this question was, and
even though it doesn't exactly connect the dots, but connecting it to
this very strict position of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is saying yes,
even so it's going to be forbidden in benefit. That's one answer
of תוספות. Let me see if I can remember the second answer.
Hold on.
I think in the most part most people felt that they didn't
feel that the people that were forbidding it didn't really understand the
מציאות, you know, didn't really understand the circumstances correctly. Those poor women
who had to destroy their wigs.
Let me just see.
Yeah, the other thing תוספות says is that maybe although it's not
clear why the גמרא is making this point right now, but oh,
because the משנה mishnah says by this, the question is why does
the משנה mishnah say, it doesn't just say that stuff that comes
out of the temple is forbidden. The משנה mishnah actually, what it
didn't say by any of the other things that it said is
forbidden, the משנה mishnah adds the clarifying words, it's forbidden because it's
זבחי מתים. zivchei meitim. Why do you have to say that? Why
don't you say the wine is forbidden because of X and the
leather with the heart cut out is because of this? Here it
specifically says it's forbidden because it's זבחי מתים. zivchei meitim. So תוספות
says that may be is the signal to the גמרא that it's
saying it's not just forbidden but it also is טמא tamei like
a dead body. And that's why we had to clarify, oh, the
idea that it's not just forbidden but that it's even טמא, tamei,
that's the position of רבי יהודה בן בתירה. Rabbi Yehuda ben Beseira.
So again, תוספות clarifies that nobody debates that the
things that are offered to עבודה זרה avodah zarah is forbidden in
benefit. Everybody agrees that. That's like rule number one. The entire משנה
mishnah that says the following things, here's a basic rule guys, if
we're not talking about meat and milk or חמץ chametz on פסח,
Pesach, then if something is forbidden in benefit it's because it's עבודה
זרה. avodah zarah. So the entire משנה mishnah that says the following
things are forbidden in benefit, of course it's all because it's related
to עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. So nobody debates that something offered to
עבודה זרה avodah zarah is forbidden in benefit. So the need to
quote רבי יהודה בן בתירה Rabbi Yehuda ben Beseira here is for
one of two reasons: either that the גמרא thinks because of the
fact that the משנה mishnah calls it זבחי מתים, zivchei meitim, it's
signaling that it has טומאה tumah like a dead body. So that's
exactly what רבי יהודה בן בתירה Rabbi Yehuda ben Beseira said. Or
it's clarifying that even though it's not a classic form of תקרובת,
tikroves, but if you take a position of רבי יהודה בן בתירה
Rabbi Yehuda ben Beseira which is a very stringent opinion, okay, then
presumably even this would be in the category of תקרובת tikroves in
order to be forbidden in benefit.
You're saying this opinion in the משנה, mishnah, which is actually ascribed...
to רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. Just as the...
I know, it is funny we skip over רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva.
Why are we associating with רבי יהודה בן בתירה Rabbi Yehuda ben
Beteira where the משנה mishna says it? Yeah, I don't know the
answer to that.
Were they contemporaries? I think, wasn't רבי יהודה בן בתירה Rabbi Yehuda
ben Beteira רבי עקיבא's... Rabbi Akiva סתם רבי יהודה stam Rabbi Yehuda
is רבי יהודה בן בתירה, Rabbi Yehuda ben Beteira, isn't it? Who's
the סתם רבי יהודה? stam Rabbi Yehuda? No,
רבי יהודה בן בבא. Rabbi Yehuda ben Bava. I thought it was
רבי יהודה בן בתירה. Rabbi Yehuda ben Beteira. If so, was a
student of רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva.
You'll find out for us. Okay, one more one more case in
the משנה, mishna, see even though we started late we're finishing, we're
going to finish okay. ההולכין לתרפות. Haholechin letarpot. תרפות, Tarpot, לתרפות? letarpot?
Okay, it's טרף, treif, anyway no it's a question of what תרפות
tarpot means anyway. Okay. תוספות says it's a play on the words
of טינופת tinofet of like filth, okay, or בית הרטופת. Beit Hartofat.
סתם רבי יהודה stam Rabbi Yehuda is רבי יהודה בר אילעאי. Rabbi
Yehuda bar Ilai.
בר אילעאי, Bar Ilai, oh that's right. Okay, right right right, בר
אילעאי. Bar Ilai. So he might be, so רבי יהודה בן בתירה
Rabbi Yehuda ben Beteira might be the same generation as רבי עקיבא.
Rabbi Akiva. You can check that out too. Anyway, so here you
have a non-Jew that is going on a... רש"י makes it sound
like almost going on a pilgrimage, okay, and he's
anyway but he's clearly going to his, you know, to...
like the Chaucer?
Yeah I know. But anyway but he's clearly going to his like
temple or maybe he's just going straight to his temple of Zeus,
okay. Here's this non-Jew and you're doing business with him. So the
משנה mishna says, can you go ahead and sell him, you know,
some clothes or some whatever, some food etc. and can you benefit
from stuff that he has on him as he's going to this
temple, on his way to this to this temple, okay? ההולכין לתרפות,
Haholechin letarpot, לתרפות? letarpot? I don't know. אסורין לשאת ולתת עמהן. Assurin
laset ulatet imahen. You can't do business with them. Why not? אמר
שמואל, Amar Shmuel, okay so we're going to say in a minute.
עובדי כוכבים הולך לתרפות, Ovdei kochavim holech letarpot, לתרפות? letarpot? I really
don't know. Anyway, בהליכה אסור דאזלו מודי קמי עבודת כוכבים. bahalicha assur
de'azlu modei kammai avodat kochavim. You can't do business with him for
the sake of... they always say תרפות? tarpot? תרפות, tarpot, okay. You
can't... and what do they say, pilgrimage? How do they translate it?
Pilgrimage?
Well here they just say festival of idolatry.
Festival? Yeah because a pilgrimage is like it's not immediate, it's like,
you know, if you read Chaucer, you're right, it's like takes them
three months to get to Lourdes or wherever it is they're going.
Anyway, okay. So he's going to some festival, okay? So so this
gets us way back to the first משנה mishna the first פרק.
perek. Don't do business because you're going to do... it's sort of
like doing business three days before their holiday. Okay, you're going to
do business and he's going to be happy he made money or
he's going to use the object he bought and somehow it's going
to increase or be offered up to his עבודה זרה. avodah zarah.
That's why don't do business on his way there. בחזרה מותר. Bachazara
mutar. When he's coming back, you can do business with him. You
know, get these nice stands right outside the temple and sell all
that cheap touristy stuff. Okay. I went to the temple of Zeus
and all I got was this lousy t-shirt.
Okay. He just did that last week in New Orleans. All right,
anyway, okay. בחזרה מותר Bachazara mutar on the way back it's permissible.
Okay, it is אדר, Adar, you know. Okay okay. So okay, why
can you do business with him on his way back? מאי דהוה
הוה. Mai de'hava hava. What was was. So he worshipped עבודה זרה
avodah zarah a minute ago. They're always worshipping עבודה זרה. avodah zarah.
Didn't we say something in another משנה mishna
in the פרק perek then? We did, after that's only רבי ישמעאל
Rabbi Ishmael that forbids after, or רבן גמליאל or whoever it was.
Yeah, someone else would disagree with this.
Maybe, maybe he would, you know, that, but but anyway it doesn't
matter, who was it, רבן גמליאל? רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Ishmael. Okay anyway,
so they're always worshipping עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, so if they did
it in the past what difference does it make for us, we
can do business with them. ישראל הולך לתרפות, Yisrael holech letarpot, now
let's say God forbid you've got a Jew who's going to participate
in this festival. The very fact that we're talking about it just
showed, you know, obviously we know this, you know, that the Jews
were involved in some of the pagan practices. I mean you go
read the נביאים, Nevi'im, you know, so completely, that's all they were
doing. Anyway, בהליכה מותר, bahalicha mutar, it's the reverse. On his way
there you can do business with him. דילמא הדר ביה ולא אזל
Dilma hadar bei velo azal because you don't have to so... even
though you see he's going to the festival, give him the benefit
of the doubt. He'll have a הרהור של תשובה. hirhur of teshuvah.
He's not going to do it, so you don't have to say
I can't do business with him because then he's going to use
it... it'll he'll use it in his worship in the festival. He's
a Jew. Even though he's going that way, maybe he'll feel better
about it, maybe he'll go and he really won't worship, you know,
who knows what he'll do. So I can go ahead and do
business with him on his way there. בחזרה אסור. Bachazara assur. Now
why can't you do it when he comes back? What's he going
to do with it now that he came back? כיון דאזיק בה,
Keivan de'azik ba, since he presumably, I don't know if בחזרה bachazara
means did anybody witness him doing it, but presumably once he actually
went, like maybe he would change his mind before he got there
and not go. But once he actually went, now you have to
assume that he actually worshipped and, you know, now you have to
assume right he's really into it, you know, so therefore you have
to assume that even though by a non-Jew maybe non-Jews do it
a little bit because that's just their norms, that's their practice, but
you know like it's true you know when you find a new
religion whichever whether it's a Jew finding the pagan religion or a
non-Jew finding Jewish religion, you get very passionate about it. Okay so
now you have to be afraid that you'll do business with him
and now he'll turn around next week and somehow it'll still feed
into his עבודה זרה avodah zarah although it's pretty funny because it's
still all in the... Still like he's not going right back to
the festival. Okay, מהדור הדור אזיל *mehadur hadur azil*, he'll go back.
So the next line is going to clarify this. והתניא *vehatanya*, didn't
we teach in a ברייתא *braisa*? ישראל הולך לתרפות בין בהליכה בין
בחזרה אסור *Yisrael holech letarfus bein behalicha bein bachazara asur*, so you
can't go in either going or coming. So אמר רב אשי *amar
Rav Ashi* כי תניא היא בישראל מומר דבאי אזיל *ki tanya hi
beYisrael mumar devai azil*. So first of all, that's a ישראל *Yisrael*
that you know. He's a guy that's like that's habitual idol worship.
So that, of course, you can't do going there, because like like
a non-Jew you can't do going, then you can't do coming back,
since again, he's so he's habitual and he's a Jew, anything is
going to feed into his עבודה זרה *avodas zara*. Who's a non-Jew
who, it's a little more just סתם *stam* practice, it's, you know,
he's not as he's not as משוגע *meshuga* about it. תנו רבנן
*tanu rabanan*, okay, I guess we'll end like that. Yes.
Where
chronologically where is the line being drawn between when we would
kill the person or do something to the person who's a Jewish
idol worshiper and when it was just accepted like this?
Yeah, probably between the first בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash* and the second.
You know, I mean the גמרא *Gemara* says that they stopped doing
דיני נפשות *dinei nefashos* towards the, you know, whatever forty years or
whatever before the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash* was destroyed, but the reality
was was that, I mean, you know, scholars point out that the
entire מסכת עבודה זרה *maseches Avodas Zara*, it never says anywhere all
the פסוקים *pesukim* that it says in the תורה *Torah* that you're
supposed to destroy the idolatry that you see in the land of
ישראל *Yisrael*, because it was a reality, you were living in pagan
Rome, nobody was going to go ahead and talk about destroying the
idols every time you walked down the street you're supposed to take
a bat with you and destroy the idols? So there was probably
a reality that nobody was, you know, even when the בית *Beis*
was around and probably trying to keep the peace, you know, and
the סנהדרין *Sanhedrin* and maybe prosecuting murderers or whatever, it probably was
not prosecuting idolaters. The discussions in סנהדרין *Sanhedrin* were probably very theoretical.
Henschel says a גרסא *girsa* of משומד *meshumad* instead of a מומר
*mumar*.
Yeah, sometimes the משומד *meshumad* is a classic replace מומר *mumar* thing.
Okay, now let's just try to get to the דף *daf*. תנו
רבנן *tanu rabanan* עובד כוכבים הולך ליריד *oved kochavim holech leyarid*, okay,
going back to first פרק *perek* stuff, going to a market day.
בין בהליכה בין בחזרה מותר *bein behalicha bein bachazara mutar*, you can
do business either way because it's just a market day, so if
it's just a market day, they're not going to be worshiping עבודה
זרה *avodas zara* there, okay?
But ישראל הולך ליריד *Yisrael holech leyarid*, a Jew that's going to
a market day, בהליכה מותר *behalicha mutar*, you can do business on
his way there, again they're not going to be עובד עבודה זרה
*oved avodas zara* at the market day, okay?
But בחזרה אסור *bechazara asur*, you can't do business on his way
back. Why not? So מאי שנא ישראל דבחזרה אסור דאמר עבודת כוכבים
זבין *mai shna Yisrael dechazara asur de'amar avodas kochavim zavin*? Because, you
know, the idea
throughout the Middle Ages and in תוספות *Tosafos* whatever you see them
trying to justify how we could sell religious items to the church,
okay? But it goes back even to the time of the גמרא
*Gemara*. The גמרא *Gemara* says the reason you can't, even though they're
not going to worship עבודה זרה *avodas zara* there, but you know,
if it's a if it's a pagan market day, a good thing
to do business in is in little pagan idols. So you're afraid
that the Jew may be sold some pagan idols, did some business,
maybe he bought it off of one guy, sold it to another,
maybe he didn't make it himself, he's just a he's just a
retailer. But whatever it is, and now some of the money in
his wallet is money from the sale of idols.
And is this specifically an idol worship fair or is it just
like?
No, yeah, a fair that's associated with.
It's not like it's like the Zeus one.
Zeus, it's the Zeus fair. Exactly, exactly. There's not they're not worshiping
עבודה זרה *avodas zara*, but it's somehow presumably it's associated with a
fair for, you know, for Dionysius or whatever it would be. They
did those types of things, right? Anyway, so therefore you have to
be afraid that he may be made some business and sold some
idols and money in his pocket is from that and you can't
get benefit from that money. Okay, so why מאי שנא ישראל דבחזרה
אסור דאמר עבודת כוכבים זבין *mai shna Yisrael dechazara asur de'amar avodas
kochavim zavin*? He sold an idol. ודמי עבודת כוכבים איכא בהדיה *udmei
avodas kochavim ika bahadei*, and he has some עבודה זרה *avodas zara*
money in his pocket. And you can't do business with him because
you'll get that money and you'll you can't get benefit from that
money. So עובד כוכבים נמי *oved kochavim nami*, so even if it's
a non-Jew who's coming back from the fair. נימא עבודת כוכבים זבין
ודמי עבודת כוכבים איכא בהדיה *neima avodas kochavim zavin udmei avodas kochavim
ika bahadei*, let's say he also was selling idols and he has
money of עבודה זרה *avodas zara* in his pocket. אלא *ela*, what
would he say? עובד כוכבים אמרינן גלימא זבין חמרא זבין *oved kochavim
amrinan glima zavin chamra zavin*. No, for a non-Jew we say, yeah,
you know, he has a חזקת כשרות *chezkas kashrus*, I'm teasing. Anyway,
for the non-Jew we say, why should we assume he sold idols?
You know, he sold he sold, you know, he maybe sold a
cloak, he maybe sold wine. Okay. So ישראל נמי נימא גלימא זבין
חמרא זבין *Yisrael nami neima glima zavin chamra zavin*?
So say a Jew also maybe sold other stuff, even if he's
making a profit, who says he's making it by selling idols? Not
sure why. No. אי אית ליה *ei is lei*, if he had
stuff to sell, okay, that was not idols, דהכא הוה מזבין ליה
*dehacha hava mazvin lei*, he would have sold it amongst in the
Jewish community. Why is he going to the non-Jewish fair? Because there's
more of them. I know, obviously there's more, maybe they have more
money, maybe he can hire higher prices, but anyway, if he's דווקא
*davka* going to their fair, we have to suspect that he's selling
stuff that he can't sell here, and we have to suspect that
he has money of עבודה זרה *avodas zara* in his pocket. Which
after I turn off the thing I'll tell you.